A Guide to the Carroll Kem Shackelford Papers, 1954-1985
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Carroll Kem Shackelford Papers, 1954-1985
Library of Virginia
32577
5.85 cubic feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Carroll Kem Shackelford, 6 August 1985.
Biographical/Historical Information
Carroll Kem Shackelford, Orange County attorney and counselor of law, was born in Newcastle, Wyoming on 22 December 1920, the daughter of James Preston Kem and Mary Elizabeth Carroll Kem. Her father served as a United States Senator from Missouri from 1947 to 1953. After obtaining an A.B. degree from Vassar College in 1940, Shackelford was employed in the field of journalism, working as an editorial assistant for Look Magazine during World War II and writing a column titled "Votes and Views" that was published in several Virginia and North Carolina newspapers. She married Virginius R. Shackelford, Jr., in 1943. In 1947, she helped establish and served for ten years on the board of the Grymes Memorial School, a non-profit private school in Orange, Virginia for children in grades 1-8. She received her law degree from the University of Virginia in 1964 and opened a law office in Culpeper, Virginia. She later became a Substitute Judge of the General District Court.
Involved in issues of interest to women, her membership on Virginia legislative committees has included the Task Force on the Equal Rights Amendment on the Law of Virginia, 1973-1974; the Subcommittee to Study Rights and Responsibilities of Spouses, 1975-1976; and the Subcommittee on Inheritance and Gift Tax Laws, 1977-1978. From 1976 to 1985, she served as counsel for the women delegates to the Virginia Legislature. Shackelford served on the board of the Library of Virginia, serving as board chairman from 1970 to 1973.
Carroll Kem Shackelford died on 22 December 2000.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1954-1985, of Carroll Kem Shackelford, Orange County attorney and counselor of law, concerning her legislative activities on the Equal Rights Amendment and other women's rights legislation. Includes speeches made concering the Equal Rights Amendment, and materials generated during her service on the Equal Rights Task Force and as counsel to the women legislators of the Virginia General Assembly. Her area of research on the Equal Rights Task Force was family law, examining how the amendment would affect the roles of mother and homemaker. The material from her role as counsel to the women legislators show the evolution of legislation on issues of concern to women, excluding the Equal Rights Amendment.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: I. Speeches, 1954-1980; II. Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) Task Force; III. Women's Rights Legislation, 1976-1985.
Series III. Women's Rights Legislation, 1976-1985, is further broken down into subseries arranged chronologically by General Assembly session. The folders under each subseries are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Folders are numbered consecutively, regardless of box, from 1-165.
Contents List
- Speeches, 1954-1980 (Box 1)
  - Re. ERA, 1954-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Re. ERA, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Re. ERA, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Re. ERA, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Re. ERA, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) Task Force (Box 1-3)
  - General (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Joint Privileges and Election Hearings, 2 February 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Reference Material (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Research (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - Hearings - Statements of Witnesses (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Hearings - Reprints, etc. filed by witnesses (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Task Force Reports (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Task Force Reports - Extra Copies (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Task Force Report and Addenda (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous clippings and letters, 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Women's Rights Legislation, 1976-1985 (Box 3-13)
  - Virginia General Assembly 1976-1977 Session (Box 3-5)
    - Bibliography and sources #1 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Bibliography and sources #2 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Courts of Justice Committee - House (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Courts of Justice Committee - Senate (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Divorce #1 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Divorce #2 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Divorce #3 - Senate and House Actions on Amendments to 20-107 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Divorce - Action on 20-107 - House (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Divorce - Action on 20-107 - Senate (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Dower and Curtesy (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Equitable Separate Estate (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Final Versions: Dower and Curtesy - Equitable separate estates (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Final Version: 4 Family Law Bills (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Final Versions and Copies (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - General (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Marital Estate - Community Property (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Meetings (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Newspaper Clippings - CKS (Carroll Kem Shackelford) (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Newspaper Clippings - General (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Newspapers Clippings re. Session (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Notes for CKS (Carroll Kem Shackelford) (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Other Bills (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Press and Television (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Status of Women (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Tax Laws (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Vote and Final Bills (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Virginia Bar Association Domestic Relations Committee (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Hoover, Eliza (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Virginia General Assembly 1977-1978 Session (Box 5-7)
    - Digest of Acts of Assembly, 1978 Regular Session (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Battered Spouses (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Employment and Job Discrimination (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Commission to Study the Containment of Health Care Costs (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Divorce - Letters re. Lump Sum Amendment (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Divorce (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Maryland Legislation (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Dower and Curtesy (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Equitable Separate Estates (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Finance Committee - Inheritance and Gift Tax Subcommittee - Expenses (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Finance Committee - General (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Finance Committee - Inheritance and Gift Tax Subcommittee Final Report (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Finance Committee - Inheritance and Gift Tax Subcommittee Forms (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Finance Committee: Inheritance and Gift Tax Subcommittee - Prior Tax Bills (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Finance Committee: Inheritance and Gift Tax Subcommittee - Meetings and Minutes (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - Finance Committee: Inheritance and Gift Tax Subcommittee Research (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - Finance Committee: Inheritance and Gift Tax Subcommittee Staff Reports (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - Inheritance Tax Law 58-152 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - Juvenile & Domestic Relations Courts - Appeal in Support Proceedings (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - Meetings - Senate and House Committee Assignments (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - Newspaper Articles (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - Paternity Actions (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - Politics (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - Press and Television (Box 7, Folder 70)
    - Suggestions for Study (Box 7, Folder 71)
    - Equal Rights Amendment (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Virginia General Assembly 1978-1979 Session (Box 8-9)
    - Digest of Acts of Assembly, 1979 Regular Session (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - Abused Spouses (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - Agreements (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Community Property (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - Correspondence and Expenses (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - Divorce #1 (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - Divorce #2 - Drafts (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - Divorce #3 (Working Papers) (Box 8, Folder 80)
    - Divorce #4 (Research) (Box 8, Folder 81)
    - Divorce #5 - House Courts of Justice Committee (Box 8, Folder 82)
    - Divorce #6 - Personal Jurisdiction - Miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 83)
    - Dower and Curtesy (Box 9, Folder 84)
    - Equitable Separate Estates (Box 9, Folder 85)
    - Finance Committee - Inheritance and Gift Tax Subcommittee - Tax Lien (Box 9, Folder 86)
    - Inheritance by Children (Box 9, Folder 87)
    - Juvenile & Domestic Relations Courts (Box 9, Folder 88)
    - Medical Insurance (Box 9, Folder 89)
    - Meetings (Box 9, Folder 90)
    - S. B. 645 - Multiple Party Accounts (Box 9, Folder 91)
    - Other Bills (Box 9, Folder 92)
    - Politics (Box 9, Folder 93)
    - Press (Box 9, Folder 94)
    - Support (Box 9, Folder 95)
    - Women Delegates - Other Bills (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - Virginia General Assembly 1979-1980 Session (Box 9-10)
    - Virginia General Assembly, 1979 and 1980 (Box 9, Folder 97)
    - Correspondence (Box 9, Folder 98)
    - Descents and Distributions (Box 10, Folder 99)
    - Divorce (Box 10, Folder 100)
    - Divorce #2 (Box 10, Folder 101)
    - Dower and Curtesy (Box 10, Folder 102)
    - Equal Rights Amendment (Box 10, Folder 103)
    - General Bills (Box 10, Folder 104)
    - Juvenile & Domestic Relations Courts (Box 10, Folder 105)
    - Marital Property (Box 10, Folder 106)
    - Politics (Box 10, Folder 107)
    - Multiple Party Accounts (Box 10, Folder 108)
    - Property Rights - VALC Study (Box 10, Folder 109)
    - Sexual Assault (Box 10, Folder 110)
    - Women's Rights - General (Box 10, Folder 111)
  - Virginia General Assembly 1980-1981 Session (Box 10)
    - Correspondence (Box 10, Folder 112)
    - Divorce and Marital Property (Box 10, Folder 113)
    - Equitable Separate Estates (Box 10, Folder 114)
    - General Bills (Box 10, Folder 115)
    - Inheritance (Box 10, Folder 116)
    - Multiple Party Accounts (Box 10, Folder 117)
    - Sexual Assault (Box 10, Folder 118)
    - Summary of Legislation for Session (Box 10, Folder 119)
  - Virginia General Assembly 1981-1982 Session (Box 11)
    - Digest of Acts of General Assembly, 1981 and 1982 Special Sessions and 1982 Session (Box 11, Folder 120)
    - Divorce - Support, Custody, Equitable Distribution Bill (Box 11, Folder 121)
    - Divorce - Support, Spousal and Child (Box 11, Folder 122)
    - Inheritance (Box 11, Folder 123)
    - Multiple Party Accounts (Box 11, Folder 124)
    - Proposals; Miscellaneous (Box 11, Folder 125)
    - Support Laws, Study of Joint Custody (Box 11, Folder 126)
    - Legislators (Box 11, Folder 127)
  - Virginia General Assembly 1982-1983 Session (Box 11)
    - Child Custody (Box 11, Folder 128)
    - Divorce - Support, Spousal and Child (Box 11, Folder 129)
    - General (Box 11, Folder 130)
    - General - Proposals - Other Bills (Box 11, Folder 131)
    - Inheritance (Box 11, Folder 132)
    - Multiple Party Accounts (Box 11, Folder 133)
    - Women's Bills - Children (Box 11, Folder 134)
  - Virginia General Assembly 1983-1984 Session (Box 11-13)
    - Digest of Acts, 1984 Session (Box 11, Folder 135)
    - Abuse - Child/Spouse (Box 11, Folder 136)
    - Children - Miscellaneous (Box 11, Folder 137)
    - Court of Appeals (Box 12, Folder 138)
    - Divorce (Box 12, Folder 139)
    - General (Box 12, Folder 140)
    - Inheritance and Estates (Box 12, Folder 141)
    - Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court (Box 12, Folder 142)
    - Other Bills (Box 12, Folder 143)
    - Paternity (Box 12, Folder 144)
    - Property Joint Subcommittee - Dower and Curtesy (Box 12, Folder 145)
    - Property Joint Subcommittee - Fall Meetings (Box 12, Folder 146)
    - Property Joint Subcommittee - General (Box 12, Folder 147)
    - Property Joint Subcommittee - Ideas Committee (Box 12, Folder 148)
    - Pay Equity (Box 13, Folder 149)
    - Summary - Women's Bills (Box 13, Folder 150)
    - Support - Child and Spouse (Box 13, Folder 151)
  - Virginia General Assembly 1984-1985 Session (Box 13)
    - Digest of Acts of Assembly, 1985 Session (Box 13, Folder 152)
    - Abortion (Box 13, Folder 153)
    - Abuse - Child and Spouse (Box 13, Folder 154)
    - Comparable Pay (Box 13, Folder 155)
    - Divorce (Box 13, Folder 156)
    - Equitable Distribution (Box 13, Folder 157)
    - Equitable Separate Estates (Box 13, Folder 158)
    - General (Box 13, Folder 159)
    - Pensions (Box 13, Folder 160)
    - Property and Inheritance (Box 13, Folder 161)
    - Pre-Marital Agreement (Box 13, Folder 162)
    - Status of Women (Box 13, Folder 163)
    - Summary of Women's Bills (Box 13, Folder 164)
    - Support - Child/Spouse (Box 13, Folder 165)